<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-12-20T14:59:14-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Catherine Rice</title><subtitle>Web developer based in NYC.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">ScriptEd</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/15/scripted.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ScriptEd" /><published>2017-12-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/15/scripted</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/15/scripted.html">&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday I had my first day of volunteering with &lt;a href=&quot;https://scripted.org/&quot;&gt;ScriptEd&lt;/a&gt;, an organization which pairs coders with students at underresourced schools in order to teach coding. I was simply observing the class on Wednesday, so I could get a sense of what the classroom was like. The kids are in 10th and 11th grades, and they were all very nice. This week was devoted to &lt;a href=&quot;https://css-tricks.com/snippets/css/a-guide-to-flexbox/&quot;&gt;flexbox&lt;/a&gt;, which to be completely honest was a topic I had to brush up on. I didn’t realize how useful flexbox is, rather than using the display and position properties and futz with those for two hours fruitlessly. There was a game called &lt;a href=&quot;https://flexboxfroggy.com/&quot;&gt;Flexbox Froggy&lt;/a&gt; in the prep material for the students, which is super fun (like any programming game).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to volunteer with ScriptEd because I think that all students, regardless of gender, socio-economic background, religion or anything, should be able to learn to code. I do truly believe that anyone can learn to code, and as an alumna of the New York City public school system, I wish we had had more computer classes in our curriculum. I think it is an invaluable skill, even if you never use it again, it is important for kids and young people (especially girls) to at least be exposed to it, so they can then decide if it is something they want to pursue more seriously. I think a lot of the gender inequality in tech is due to education, and the inequality can be addressed in elementary, middle and high school. So, I am excited to volunteer and teach coding basics through ScriptEd next year!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">On Wednesday I had my first day of volunteering with ScriptEd, an organization which pairs coders with students at underresourced schools in order to teach coding. I was simply observing the class on Wednesday, so I could get a sense of what the classroom was like. The kids are in 10th and 11th grades, and they were all very nice. This week was devoted to flexbox, which to be completely honest was a topic I had to brush up on. I didn’t realize how useful flexbox is, rather than using the display and position properties and futz with those for two hours fruitlessly. There was a game called Flexbox Froggy in the prep material for the students, which is super fun (like any programming game).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Web Dev Glossary</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/11/glossary.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Web Dev Glossary" /><published>2017-12-11T14:33:57-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-11T14:33:57-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/11/glossary</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/11/glossary.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m putting together a glossary or dictionary of common web development terms that I find myself always looking up, because even if I have heard a particular term before, I still don’t have a good grasp of the concept. One way that I study, in general, is just by compiling a list of terms and ideas that keep coming up, that I know are important, and recording definitions and sometimes examples from different sources (Wikipedia, a coding website in this case like StackOverflow) and I find it helps me remember things more. So far I have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;npm&lt;/strong&gt;:
package manager for the JavaScript programming language - default package manager for the JavaScript runtime environment node.js
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Node.js&lt;/strong&gt;:
an open-source, cross-platform JavaScript run-time environment for executing JavaScript server-side
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Run-time system&lt;/strong&gt;:
implements portions of an execution model
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Scripting/script language&lt;/strong&gt;:
programming language that supports scripts: programs writen for a special run-time environment that automate the execution of tasks that could alternatively be executed one-byone by a human operator
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;web API endpoint&lt;/strong&gt;:
a server-side web API is a programmatic interface consisting of one or more publicly exposed endpoints to a defined request - response message system expressed in JSON or XML, which is exposed via the web, most commonly by means of an HTTP-based web server
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m putting together a glossary or dictionary of common web development terms that I find myself always looking up, because even if I have heard a particular term before, I still don’t have a good grasp of the concept. One way that I study, in general, is just by compiling a list of terms and ideas that keep coming up, that I know are important, and recording definitions and sometimes examples from different sources (Wikipedia, a coding website in this case like StackOverflow) and I find it helps me remember things more. So far I have:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Object-oriented JavaScript</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/07/post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Object-oriented JavaScript" /><published>2017-12-07T14:33:57-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-07T14:33:57-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/07/post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/07/post.html">&lt;p&gt;Today I spent some time reviewing object-oriented JavaScript, or OOJS for short, through a course called Frontend Masters. Although JavaScript does not have formal classes the way Ruby or other object-oriented languages do, the constructor function can act like a class in that it can act like a blueprint for creating new instances of objects. The prototype property is used to add methods to existing constructors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today I spent some time reviewing object-oriented JavaScript, or OOJS for short, through a course called Frontend Masters. Although JavaScript does not have formal classes the way Ruby or other object-oriented languages do, the constructor function can act like a class in that it can act like a blueprint for creating new instances of objects. The prototype property is used to add methods to existing constructors.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making a Jekyll Site</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/05/test-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making a Jekyll Site" /><published>2017-12-05T14:33:57-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-05T14:33:57-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/05/test-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/05/test-post.html">&lt;p&gt;This is my first post using &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, a static site generator. Initially I didn’t really know what the purpose of Jekyll was, but now I see that it uses a collection of layouts to create a general template for a static website or blog. The main theme has a very nice looking design, very minimalist (actually it’s called “Minima”). I do feel a little bit guilty using a site generator, especially after learning Rails and knowing how to incorporate a fair bit of Bootstrap or Materialize CDNs. But, I decided I’m just going to use it to get a personal website up and running and have a place to display projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although, as this dude Mike discusses in one of his tutorial videos on Jekyll &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZtEbGztktvc&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, Jekyll can be useful and fun for both someone with little to no programming experience or someone who wants to customize and change the layout files, etc. For example, I just learned about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yaml.org/&quot;&gt;YAML&lt;/a&gt;. (It is NOT a markup language) but is actually a “human-readable data serialization language commonly used for configuration files”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is my first post using Jekyll, a static site generator. Initially I didn’t really know what the purpose of Jekyll was, but now I see that it uses a collection of layouts to create a general template for a static website or blog. The main theme has a very nice looking design, very minimalist (actually it’s called “Minima”). I do feel a little bit guilty using a site generator, especially after learning Rails and knowing how to incorporate a fair bit of Bootstrap or Materialize CDNs. But, I decided I’m just going to use it to get a personal website up and running and have a place to display projects.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to my website!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/01/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to my website!" /><published>2017-12-01T14:33:57-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-01T14:33:57-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/01/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/12/01/welcome-to-jekyll.html">&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone! Welcome to my Jekyll website. Here I will post about projects I’m working on, things I’m learning (web development wise), and any progress on my job search.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Hi everyone! Welcome to my Jekyll website. Here I will post about projects I’m working on, things I’m learning (web development wise), and any progress on my job search.</summary></entry></feed>